Guide to the Duke University Medical Center Reference Collection, 1941-ongoing
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Duke University Medical Center Reference collection 1941-ongoing
University Archives, Duke University
Duke University. University Archives
0.7 Linear Feet 750 Items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Duke University Medical Center Reference Collection was compiled from a variety of sources by the University Archives for use in reference and research.
Historical Note
timeline excerpted from Duke Medical Center Archives http://archives.mc.duke.edu/history/timeline.html
In 1924, James Buchanan Duke established the Duke Endowment and directed that 6 million of the endowment be used to transform Trinity College into Duke University. He made an additional bequest to the Endowment and the University, in 1925, which included $4 million towards the establishment of a medical school, hospital and nurses home.
Chronology List
1927 Dr. Wilburt Cornell Davison elected Dean of the Duke University School of Medicine and Hospital on 21 January.
Construction begins on the Medical School and Duke Hospital.
1929 3,000 applicants apply to the new medical school. 70 first- and third-year students are selected, including four women.
1930 Duke Hospital opens July 20, 1930, attracting 25,000 visitors.
Classes began in Hospital Administration, dietetics, and medical technology on 15 August.
The eighteen third year and thirty first year medical students began classes on 2 October.
1931 The Duke School of Nursing's first class of 24 undergraduate students begin classes January 2. Private Diagnostic Clinics were organized 15 September.
1935 The Association of American Medical Colleges ranks Duke among the top 25 percent of medical schools in the country-less than five years after it opened.
1936 Duke surgeons led by Dr. J. Deryl Hart pioneer the use of ultraviolet lamps in operating rooms to eliminate infectious organisms that cause post-operative Staph infections. This procedure dramatically reduces the number of infections and related deaths.
1937 Dr. Joseph Beard developed a vaccine against equine encephalomyelitis.
Duke establishes the nation's first brain tumor program, launching what will become one of the world's foremost cancer programs.
1940 First wing added to Duke Hospital.
For his studies of the metabolism of the tubercle bacillus, which eventually led to effective medications, pharmacologist Frederick Bernheim is nominated for the Nobel Prize.
1940s-1950s Dr. Walter Kempner's research, using a rice-based diet and daily laboratory testing, demonstrates that degenerative processes attacking the kidney, heart, brain and retina can be arrested by dietary changes. These dramatic findings draw patients to Duke from across the nation.
1955 Psychiatrist Ewald W. Busse establishes the Duke University Center for Aging, the first research center of its kind in the nation. Now the oldest continuously running aging center in the United States, the Duke Center for Aging has pioneered long-term studies of health problems among the elderly.
1959 Duke develops a machine that lowers patients' blood temperatures below 68 degrees Fahrenheit and is the first to place a patient under this deep hypothermia during open-heart surgery.
1963 First African-American student admitted to Duke University School of Medicine.
1980 The new $94.5 million, 616-bed Duke Hospital opens, bringing the total number of patient beds to more than 1,000.
1992 Duke Comprehensive Cancer Center develops the nation's first outpatient bone-marrow transplantation program.
1998 The Duke University Health System - an integrated academic health care system serving a broad area of central North Carolina - is officially created as Duke establishes partnerships with Durham Regional Hospital, Raleigh Community Hospital, and other regional health care providers. DUHS today includes three hospitals, ambulatory care and surgery clinics, primary care medical practice clinics, home health services, hospice services, physician practice affiliations, managed care providers and other related facilities and services.
Collection Overview
The Duke University Medical Center Reference Collection contains clippings, handbooks, reports, newsletters, and other printed material relating to Duke University Medical Center its departments, employees, and other related matters. This collection was compiled from a variety of sources by the University Archives for use in reference and research.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Academic medical centers -- North Carolina -- Durham -- History
Duke University Health System
Duke University. Medical Center -- History
Duke University. Medical Center
Related Material
see also Duke Medical Center Archives http://archives.mc.duke.edu/index.html
Barnes Woodhall, Chancellor, Records, 1969-1970.
University Archives. Duke University.
Duke Insider, 1989-1991.
University Archives. Duke University.
Educational Facilities Committee records, 1962-1986.
University Archives. Duke University.
H. Keith H. Brodie, Chancellor, records, 1963-1994.
University Archives. Duke University.
J. Deryl Hart records, 1959-1980 (bulk 1960-1963).
University Archives. Duke University.
Patent Administration Records, 1957-1988.
University Archives. Duke University.
Detailed Description of Collection
- Container List, 1 Box
  - Administration, 1926-1978 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Health System, 1999
  - The Quest for Excellence: A Growth Policy and Planning Document…, 1984
  - Duke University Medical Center Long Range Plan, 1991
  - Duke University Medical Center Long Range Plan, 1997
  - Duke Hospital, clippings, 1991
  - Duke Hospital, merger with Durham Regional Hospital, 1997-1998
  - Time Magazine:A Week in the Life of a Hospital, 1998 October 12
  - Highland Hospital, [1939 ca. April 23]
  - Raleigh Community Hospital, 1999
  - Histories, 1937-
  - D.U.M.C: The Early Days, Olga Marx Perlzweig, 1984
  - Clippings, 1974-
  - Handbooks and patient guides, 1957-2001 (2 folders)
  - Employees and workforce issues, 1994-
  - Nursing Services, Dept. of, Nursing Connections [newsletter], 1991-1996
  - Audiovisual Education Division
  - Center for Living, 1999
  - Cultural Services Program, 2000
  - Diet programs, 1974-
  - Family Medicine, 1985-
  - Pastoral Services, 1986-
  - Physician Assistant Program, 1968-
  - Public Relations Office, 1983-
  - Duke University's Preventive Approach to Cardiology (DUPAC), 1975- (Box 2)
  - Inside Track, [DUPAC newsletter], 1985-1987, 1991-1992
  - School of Medicine - brochures
  - Alumni
  - Alumni Association
  - Library, 1980
  - Library, Trent Collection
    - General
    - Announcements
    - Newsletters, 1987/88
    - Trent Associates Report, 1993-2002
  - Personal Rapid Transit (PRT) System, 1977-1982
  - Children's Miracle Network telethon, 1985
  - Nearly New Shoppe, 1979, 1984
  - Electron microscope, 1941
  - Research and discoveries
  - Journal of Health Policy, Politics and Law
  - The Special Chart [Nursing], 1950
  - Teamwork [newsletter], 1998-
  - Duke Health Line, 1985-1991